

COMPUTATIONAL SCIENTIST · APPLIED MATHEMATICIAN

San Francisco, California

□+1510-388-2095 | ☑ daancamps@gmail.com | 🏕 daancamps.com | 🖸 campsd | 🛅 campsd |

Dated: December 1, 2024.

Quantum computing and high perfomance computing (HPC) engineer in the Advanced Technologies Group at the National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center (NERSC) at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory. Working on the leading edge of technology, integrating quantum technologies with future HPC systems, and developing a quantum computing program at NERSC. Over 5 years research experience in quantum information and quantum algorithms, 9+ years experience in computational mathematics, and 2+ years experience as project engineer. Recent collaborations resulted in a robust publication record of 20 journal articles and 5 conference papers.

Work Experience

National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center (NERSC), Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

Berkeley, USA

QUANTUM COMPUTING AND HPC ARCHITECTURE AND PERFORMANCE ENGINEER IN ADVANCED TECHNOLOGIES GROUP

Apr. 2022 - Current

- Working on integrating HPC with future quantum technologies,
- Benchmarking of heterogeneous quantum-classical systems,
- Developing and driving NERSC's quantum computing program and strategy,
- Research on quantum algorithms for scientific computing.

Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

Berkeley, USA

POSTDOCTORAL RESEARCHER IN COMPUTATIONAL MATHEMATICS

Nov. 2019 - Apr. 2022

- Research on quantum information and quantum algorithms with a focus on circuit compilation and synthesis,
- Completed projects on Hamiltonian simulation, quantum chemistry, quantum linear algebra, and quantum image processing,
- Software engineering of nonlinear tensor factorization package,
- Developed QCLAB, QCLAB++, F3C, F3C++, QPIXL++ and FunFact, FABLE,
- Team scientist.

KU Leuven, Belgium

TEACHING ASSISTANT Sep. 2015 - Jun. 2019

- Exercise sessions for courses on numerical modeling and approximation, numerical mathematics,
- Mentor of master student projects.

IPCOS NV Leuven, Belgium

PROJECT ENGINEER IN DIGITAL OILFIELD TEAM

Aug. 2013 - Sep. 2015

- Deployment and maintenance of upstream production monitoring models based on real-time process data,
- Development and deployment of new data-driven pipeline leak detection models,
- Customer-oriented role: presenting on-site training sessions and providing end user support.

Skills, Competencies & Training

Programming

- MATLAB, C++, Python, Fortran 90.
- OpenMP and MPI.
- git, CMake
- QCLAB and QCLAB++: quantum circuit development, analysis and simulation.
- F3C and F3C++: fast and scalable quantum circuit compilation for Hamiltonian simulation.

Open source projects

- QPIXL++: efficient and compressible representations for quantum images.
- FunFact: tensor algebra and deep learning via Einstein notations.
- FABLE: generate quantum circuits for block encodings.

Research interests

Quantum algorithms, Scalable quantum benchmarking, Quantum circuit synthesis, Numerical linear algebra, Tensor decomposition techniques, Manifold optimization, Eigenvalue problems, Randomized algorithms, Scientific machine learning,

• Communications Excellence (Haas Business School, UC Berkeley, 2023)

Formal training

- Mathematics of Big Data: Sketching and (Multi-)Linear Algebra (MSRI Graduate Summer School, 2021)
- Fundamentals of Machine Learning (SOCN Graduate School, 2018)
- Low-Rank Tensor Techniques (Haussdorff School, 2016)

Personal & Communication

Languages

- · Dutch: Native
- English: Fluent
- French: Moderate
- TA for B.Sc. courses on numerical modeling and approximation, numerical mathematics at KU Leuven.

Teaching & Mentorship

- Mentor of M.Sc. thesis projects at KU Leuven.
- Mentor of summer interns at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.
- Mentor of postdoctoral researchers at Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory.

Publications & Preprints

- **The RQR algorithm, Camps D.**, T. Mach, R. Vandebril, D. S. Watkins, arXiv:2411.17671. **Long-lived oscillations of metastable states in neutral atom systems,** Darbha S., Kornjača M.,
- 2024 Liu F., Balewski J., Hirsbrunner M. R., Lopes P., Wang S., Van Beeumen R., Klymko K., Camps D., Phys. Rev. B 110, 155114, arXiv:2404.12371.
 - False vacuum decay and nucleation dynamics in neutral atom systems, Darbha S., Kornjača
- 2024 M., Liu F., Balewski J., Hirsbrunner M. R., Lopes P., Wang S., Van Beeumen R., Camps D., Klymko K., Phys. Rev. B 110, 155103, arXiv:2404.12360.
- **Efficient Measurement-Driven Eigenenergy Estimation with Classical Shadows,** Shen Y., Buzali A., Hu H.-Y., Klymko K., Camps D., Yelin S. F., Van Beeumen R., arXiv:2409.13691.
- Non-Clifford diagonalization for measurement shot reduction in quantum expectation value estimation, Sawaya N., Camps D., Tubman N., Rotskoff G., LaRose R., arXiv:2408.11898.
- **Quantum Rational Transformation Using Linear Combinations of Hamiltonian Simulations,** Shen Y., Van Buggenhout N., Camps D., Klymko K., Van Beeumen R., arXiv:2408.07742.
- Quantum-centric supercomputing for materials science: A perspective on challenges and future directions, Future Generation Computer Systems, DOI:10.1016/j.future.2024.04.060

 Evaluation of the classical hardware requirements for large-scale quantum computations,
- 2024 Camps D., Rrapaj E., Klymko K., Austin B., Wright N.J. Proceedings of ISC-HPC24 Conference, DOI:10.23919/ISC.2024.10528937
- **Engineering quantum states with neutral atoms,** Balewski J., Kornjača M., Klymko K., Darbha S., Hirsbrunner M. R., Lopes P., Liu F., Camps D. arXiv:2404.04411.
- 2024 Explicit Quantum Circuits for Block Encodings of Certain Sparse Matrices, Camps D., Lin L., Van Beeumen R., Yang C., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 45(1)DOI:10.1137/22M1484298, arXiv:2203.10236.

 Quantum-parallel vectorized data encodings and computations on trapped-ions and
- **transmon QPUs**, Balewski J., Amankwah M., Van Beeumen R., Bethel E., Perciano T., Camps D. Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-024-53720-x, arXiv:2301.07841.
- 2024 Simple Diagonal Designs with Reconfigurable Real-Time Circuits, Shen Y., Klymko K., Rabani E., Camps D., Van Beeumen R., Lindsey M. arXiv:2401.04176.
- 2024 Simulating dirty bosons on a quantum computer, Bassman Oftelie L., Van Beeumen R., Camps D., de Jong W., Dupont M., New Journal of Physics, DOI:10.1088/1367-2630/ad1a2d, arXiv:2210.08386.
- **k-Commutatitivity and Measurement Reduction for Expectation Values,** DelFavero B., Sarkar R., Camps D., Sawaya N., LaRose R. arXiv:2312.11840.
- **Quantum-centric Supercomputing for Materials Science: A Perspective on Challenges and Future Directions**, arXiv:2312.09733.

- A Performance Model for Estimating the Cost of Scaling to Practical Quantum Advantage,
- 2023 Camps D., Klymko K., Austin B., Wright N. J., A, Proceedings of the SC '23 Workshops of The International Conference on High Performance Computing, Network, Storage, and Analysis, DOI:10.1145/3624062.3625533.
 - Efficient Quantum Counting and Quantum Content-Addressable Memory for DNA
- **2023** *similarity*, Balewski J., Camps D., Klymko K., Tritt A, 2023 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE), DOI:10.1109/QCE57702.2023.00050, arXiv:2308.00699. *HamLib: A library of Hamiltonians for benchmarking quantum algorithms and hardware*,
- Sawaya N., Marti-Dafcik D., Ho Y., Tabor D., Bernal D., Magann A., Premaratne S., Dubey P., Matsuura A., de Jong W., Benjamin S., Parekh O., Tubman N., Klymko K., Camps D. arXiv:2306.13126. Accepted in Quantum.
 - Estimating Eigenenergies from Quantum Dynamics: A Unified Noise-Resilient
- **Measurement-Driven Approach**, Shen Y., Camps D., Darbha S., Szasz A., Klymko K., Williams-Young D., Tubman N., Van Beeumen R. arXiv:2306.01858.
 - Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits: Particle Creation, Arbitrary
- **2023** *Lattices and Controlled Evolution*, Kökcü E., Camps D., Bassman Oftelie L., de Jong W., Van Beeumen R., Kemper A. arXiv:2303.09538.
- 2023 *QCLAB++: Simulating Quantum Circuits on GPUs*, Van Beeumen R., Camps D., Mehta N. arXiv:2303.00123.
 - Exploring Finite Temperature Properties of Materials with Quantum Computers, Powers C.,
- **2023** Bassman Oftelie L., Camps D., de Jong W. A., Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-023-28317-5, arXiv:2205.00081.
 - FABLE: Fast Approximate Quantum Circuits for Block-Encodings, Camps D., Van Beeumen R.
- 2022 IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE), DOI: 10.1109/QCE53715.2022.00029, arXiv:2205.00081.
 - Quantum pixel representations and compression for N-dimensional images, Amankwah M.
- **2022** G., Camps D., Bethel E.W., Van Beeumen R., Perciano T. Scientific Reports, DOI: 10.1038/s41598-022-11024-y.
 - Algebraic compression of quantum circuits for Hamiltonian evolution, Kökcü E., Camps D.,
- 2022 Bassman L., Freericks J.K., de Jong W.A., Van Beeumen R., Kemper A.F., Phys. Rev. A,DOI:10.1103/PhysRevA.105.032420.
 - An algebraic quantum circuit compression algorithm for Hamiltonian simulation, Camps D.,
- **2021** Kökcü E., Bassman L., de Jong W.A., Kemper A.F., Van Beeumen R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 43(3), DOI:10.1137/21M1439298,arXiv:2108.03283.
- **A multishift, multipole rational QZ method with aggressive early deflation,** Steel T., Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 42(2), 753–774. DOI: 10.1137/19M1249631
- 2020 Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings, Camps D., Van Beeumen R., Phys. Rev. A 102, 052411. DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevA.102.052411
 - Chemistry on quantum computers with virtual quantum subspace expansion, Urbanek M., Camps D., Van Beeumen R., de Jong W. A., J. Chem. Theory Comput. 16(9), 5425–5431. DOI:
- **2020** Camps D., Van Beeumen R., de Jong W. A., J. Chem. Theory Comput. 16(9), 5425–5431. DOI: 10.1021/acs.jctc.0c00447
- **Quantum Fourier transform revisited**, Camps D., Van Beeumen R., Yang C., Numer. Linear Algebra Appl. 28(1). DOI: 10.1002/nla.2331
- **On pole-swapping algorithms for the eigenvalue problem, Camps D.,** Mach T., Vandebril R., Watkins D. S., Electron. Trans. Numer. Anal. 52, 480–508. DOI: 10.1553/etna_vol52s480
- Swapping 2x2 blocks in the Schur and generalized Schur form, Camps D., Mastronardi N., Vandebril R., Van Dooren P., J. Comput. Appl. Math. 373. 112274. DOI: 10.1016/j.cam.2019.05.022
- 2019 *A rational QZ method*, Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., SIAM J. Matrix Anal. Appl. 40(3), 943–972. DOI: 10.1137/18M1170480
- An implicit filter for rational Krylov using core transformations, Camps D., Meerbergen K., Vandebril R., Linear Algebra and its Applications, DOI: 10.1016/j.laa.2018.09.021

 Block term decomposition for modelling epileptic seizures, Hunyadi B., Camps D., Sorber L.,
- 2014 Van Paesschen W., De Vos M., Van Huffel S., De Lathauwer L., EURASIP Journal on Advances in Signal Processing, DOI: 10.1186/1687-6180-2014-139

Education

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

PhD in Computer Science and Applied Mathematics

Leuven, Belgium Sep. 2015 - Sep. 2019

- Thesis: Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem Rational QR algorithms.
- Generalized dense QR eigenvalue algorithms to rational QR methods.
- Implicitly restarted rational Krylov methods for large-scale, sparse eigenvalue problems.
- Focus on theory, numerical stability and efficient implementations.

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

M.Sc.Eng. in Mathematical Engineering

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2013

• Thesis: 'Epileptic seizure monitoring using tensor decomposition techniques'.

KU Leuven (University of Leuven)

Leuven, Belgium

Leuven, Belgium

M.Sc. in Physics: Astronomy and Astrophysics

Sep. 2009 - Sep. 2011

• Thesis: 'Heschel/PACS observations of water in the carbon-rich AGB star V Hya'.

UHasselt (University of Hasselt)

Hasselt, Belgium

B.Sc. IN PHYSICS

Sep. 2006 - Jun. 2010

Talks_

ieratec worksnop	Reims, France
From HamLib to HamPerf: A Hamiltonian-Oriented Approach to Quantum Benchmarking	June 2024
ISC High Performance 2024 Final partial partial partial bandware requirements for large coals quantum computations	Hamburg, Germany
Evaluation of the classical hardware requirements for large-scale quantum computations	May 2024

DW75 Workshop

APS March Meeting

Leuven, Belgium May 2024

On Block Encodings of Matrices

Minneapolis, MN, USA

Exploring the Lieb lattice phase diagram using Rydberg atom quantum simulators

March 2024

SC23 – The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and Analysis

Denver, CO
November 2023

A Performance Model for Estimating the Cost of Scaling to Practical Quantum Advantage

Virtual

Intel Labs Quantum Seminar Series

September 2023

Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits

Tokyo, Japan

FunFact: Tensor Decomposition, Your Way

August 2023

IonQ Quantum Seminar Series

Virtual May 2023

Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits

San Francisco, CA, USA

Guest lecture at San Francisco State University
Algebraic Compression of Free Fermionic Quantum Circuits

April 2023

APS March Meeting

10th International Congress on Industrial and Applied Mathematics

Las Vegas, NV, USA March 2023

Classical and Quantum Strategies to Boost Quantum Subspace Methods

Broomfield, CO, USA

*IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering*FABLE: Fast Approximate Quantum Circuits for Block-Encodings

September 2022

XXI Householder Symposium on Numerical Linear Algebra

Selva di Fasano, Italy June 2022

An Algebraic Quantum Circuit Compression Algorithm for Hamiltonian Simulation

Berkeley, USA

CS Area 3rd Annual Postdoc Symposium
FunFact: a Tensor Algebra Language with Applications in Deep Learning

Feb. 2022 Virtual

SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra

May 2021

Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings

AIDE-QC All-Hands Meeting Virtual An Algebraic and Scalable Synthesis Algorithm for Computing Dynamic Simulation Apr. 2021 Constant-Depth Circuits APS March Meeting Virtual Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings Mar. 2021 SIAM Conference on Computational Science and Engineering Virtual Understanding the quantum Fourier transform through matrix decompositions Mar. 2021 QIP Conference Virtual (Munich, Germany) Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings Feb. 2021 CS Area 2nd Annual Postdoc Symposium Berkeley, USA Approximate quantum circuit synthesis using block encodings Feb. 2021 Berkeley Lab Seminar Berkeley, USA Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem – Rational QR algorithms Sep. 2019 ICIAM Conference Valencia, Spain Pole swapping methods for the eigenvalue problem – Rational QR algorithms Jul. 2019 ETNA25 Conference Sardinia, Italy Approximate inverse-free rational Krylov methods and the link with FOM and GMRES May 2019 NASCA Conference Kalamata, Greece A rational QZ method Jul. 2018 SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra Hong Kong RQZ: A rational QZ method for the generalized eigenvalue problem May. 2018 NUMA Internal Seminar Leuven, Belgium Rational matrix algorithms for the generalized eigenvalue problem — Iterative and direct Oct. 2017 methods ILAS Conference Iowa, USA Implicit restart of the rational Krylov method — Chasing algorithms for polynomial, Jul. 2017 extended and rational Krylov ILAS Conference Leuven, Belgium Towards a computational efficient, implicitly restarted rational Krylov method Jul. 2016

Academic service

IOP New Journal of Physics, ACM Transactions on Quantum Computing, IEEE Transactions on Quantum Engineering, npj Quantum Information, Quantum – the open

journal for quantum science, Quantum Information & Computation, Journal of

Reviewer for Computational Physics, Applied Mathematics and Computation, SIAM Journal on Matrix Analysis and Applications, Linear and Multilinear Algebra, Electronic Transactions on

Numerical Analysis, IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and

Engineering, The Journal of Supercomputing

Program Committee for IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering 2022 & 2024

Honors & Awards

1st Place Best Research Paper in Quantum Technologies and Systems Engineering (QTEM)

track, IEEE International Conference on Quantum Computing and Engineering (QCE24).

2024 Hans Meuer Award for Best Research Paper, ISC High Performance.

2018 *SIAM Student Travel Award*, SIAM Conference on Applied Linear Algebra.

Montreal, Canada Hamburg, Germany Hong Kong